Guide to the Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs, 1930-2010 TJU.2010.01.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs
1930-2010
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Specter, Arlen
TJU.2010.01.09
3 boxes 3 records center boxes, plus oversize material
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs contains photographs documenting Senator Specter's career and personal life. Specter served as U.S. Senator from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured Pennsylvanian senator.
Custodial History
Material was transferred to the care of Philadelphia University in 2010-2011 from the Federal Records Storage Facility in Suitland, Maryland, as well as the Senator's Washington, D.C. and Pennsylvania offices. The physical material was transferred to the University of Pittsburgh in 2014, with the exception of selected photographic and memorabilia items that remain at the Arlen Specter Center's Roxboro House for display. In 2016, Philadelphia University merged with Thomas Jefferson University, and is now known as Thomas Jefferson University- East Falls campus.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arlen Specter to Philadelphia University in 2010. Philadelphia University and the University of Pittsburgh entered into a partnership to jointly manage the collection in 2013.
Biography
Born in Wichita, Kansas, on February 12, 1930, Arlen Specter came to Pennsylvania to attend the University of Pennsylvania. He married Joan Levy in 1953, and graduated from Yale Law School in 1956. He became assistant district attorney in Philadelphia in 1959. In 1962, Specter was recommended to serve on the Warren Commission, assembled to investigate the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. As part of the Commission, he was responsible for co-authoring the proposal of the "single bullet theory," determining that one bullet struck both President Kennedy and Texas Governor John Connally. Specter ran for Philadelphia district attorney in 1965, switching his Party membership to Republican in order to unseat the incumbent Democrat. He was successful, and served as district attorney from 1966 to 1974.
After an initial failed run for Senator and then for Governor of Pennsylvania, Specter was elected to the U.S. Senate in 1980. He would stay in this position from 1981 to 2011, making him the longest-tenured senator in Pennsylvania's history. During this time, he was a member of a number of Committees: Judiciary (1981-2011; Chair, 2007-2007), Appropriations (1981-2011), Veterans Affairs (1981-2011; Chair, 1997-2001 and 2003-2005), Select Intelligence (1985-1991; 1995-1997; Chair, 1995-1997), Special Aging (1991-1995; 2007-2011), Governmental Affairs (1997-2001; 2003-2005), and Environment and Public Works (2001-2003; 2009-2011).
Though elected as a Republican, Specter was a moderate on many issues, including healthcare reform, immigration, and abortion. He would often cross party lines, such as in voting against the confirmation of President Ronald Reagan's nominee Judge Robert Bork to the Supreme Court in 1987. Specter would again come into the spotlight during a Supreme Court nomination process in 1991, for his cross-examination of Professor Anita Hill regarding her allegations against nominee Clarence Thomas. In 1999, he would vote against the charges brought against President Bill Clinton, giving an answer of "not proven" to reflect his belief that Clinton had not received a fair trial.
As Senator, Specter championed a number of causes and influenced many legislative areas. He was frequently a member of Congressional Delegation trips, particularly to the Middle East, where he would speak out on the cause of freedom from religious persecution and the importance of strong diplomatic relations. He was also a proponent of funding for medical research, including the use of stem cells. He advocated for strict crime laws, particularly for career criminals. His focus on benefitting Pennsylvania could be seen through the pursuit of grant funding opportunities and his attempt to prevent the closure of the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard in the 1990s.
With the worsening of Congressional partisanship in the late 2000s, Specter found himself frequently voting with his Democratic peers. After being one of only three handful of Republicans to vote for the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act in 2009, Specter found himself increasingly marginalized within his party. In April 2009, he returned to the Democratic Party, helping to ensure the passage of the Affordable Care Act. Seeking re-election in 2010, he was defeated in the Democratic primary by Joe Sestak.
Specter's 30-year tenure in the Senate concluded in January 2011. After leaving the Senate, he partnered with Philadelphia University (now Jefferson-East Falls) to establish the Arlen Specter Center for Public Service. In the fall of 2012, Specter, who had previously beaten Hodgkin's lymphoma in 2005 while serving as Chair of the Judiciary Committee, was diagnosed with cancer. He died on October 14, 2012, aged 82.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
The Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 9. Photographs comprises 3 boxes of material, plus additional oversized items, and contains photographs documenting Senator Specter's career and personal life. In addition to the material described in this guide, additional oversized and framed items are available; interested researchers should contact Archives & Special Collections for the oversize inventory list.
Arrangement
Group 9 is arranged alphabetically by topic. Oversize material is arranged by size as space allows, and is not in a specific order. Interested researchers should contact Archives & Special Collection for an inventory of the oversized material.
Related Material
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 1. Pre-Senatorial Career Files, 1953-1980, TJU.2010.01.01
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 2. Legislative Files, 1965-2011, TJU.2010.01.02
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 3. Personal, Political and Official Files, 1944-2010, TJU.2010.01.03
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 4. Office Administration Files, 1962-2010, TJU.2010.01.04
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 5. Constituent Services Files, 1976-2007, TJU.2010.01.05
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 6. Public Relations and Media Files, 1972-2010, TJU.2010.01.06
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 7. Campaign Files, 1976-2004, TJU.2010.01.07
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 8. Awards and Memorabilia, 1957-2010, TJU.2010.01.08
Arlen Specter Senatorial Papers, Group 10. Electronic Records, 1980-2010, TJU.2010.01.10
China; Taiwan; Photographs; Politicians; Government; Korea (South); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Specter, Arlen; United States. Congress. Senate; Assad, Bashar; Assad, Hafez; Hussein, Saddam; Bush, Barbara; Bush, George Walker; Bush, George, H.W (Herbert Walker); Reagan, Ronald W. (Ronald Wilson); Hillman, Elsie Hilliard; Arafat, Yasir; Thurmond, Strom; Santorum, Rick; Al Gore; Hope, Bob; Dole, Robert J.; Ridge, Thomas J.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); Heinz, John; Ford, Gerald R.; Carter, Jimmy; Clinton, Bill
- Abdullah II of Jordan, 2006 (Box 1336, Folder 1)
- African-Americans, 1982-1986 and undated (Box 1336, Folder 2)
- Agriculture, 1984-1990 and undated (Box 1336, Folder 3)
- Airplanes, undated (Box 1336, Folder 4)
- Alaska, 2001 (Box 1336, Folder 5)
- Bashar al-Assad, undated (Box 1336, Folder 6)
- Hafez al-Assad, 1997 (Box 1336, Folder 7)
- Madeleine Albright, undated (Box 1336, Folder 8)
- Alliance for Legislative and Political Action, 1990 (Box 1336, Folder 9)
- Yasser Arafat, undated (Box 1336, Folder 10)
- Army/Navy football game, 1989 (Box 1336, Folder 11)
- Atlanta, 1991 (Box 1336, Folder 12)
- Awards, 1982-1999 and undated (Box 1336, Folder 13)
- Baby photo, 1930 (Box 1336, Folder 14)
- Prince Hassan bin Talal, 1998 (Box 1336, Folder 15)
- Birthday, undated (Box 1336, Folder 16)
- B'nai B'rith Board of Governors, 1990 (Box 1336, Folder 17)
- Robert Bork, 1987 (Box 1336, Folder 18)
- Budget signing, 1997 (Box 1336, Folder 19)
- Barbara Bush, undated (Box 1336, Folder 20)
- George H.W. Bush, 1989-1992 and undated (Box 1336, Folder 21)
- George W. Bush, 2006 (Box 1336, Folder 22)
- Campaign, 1992 (Box 1336, Folder 23)
- Campaign, 1998 (Box 1336, Folder 24)
- Campaign, 2004 (Box 1336, Folder 25)
- Jimmy Carter, 1994 (Box 1336, Folder 26)
- Fidel Castro, 1999 (Box 1336, Folder 27)
- China, 2001 (Box 1336, Folder 28-29)
- Cities and urban tours, 1982 and undated (Box 1336, Folder 30)
- Citizens for Arlen Specter Day, 1991 (Box 1336, Folder 31)
- Bill Clinton, 1994-1997 (Box 1336, Folder 32)
- Constituents, undated (Box 1336, Folder 33)
- Construction site, undated (Box 1336, Folder 34)
- Defense, 1983-1984 and undated (Box 1336, Folder 35)
- Suleyman Demirel, 1998 (Box 1336, Folder 36)
- District Attorney photos, 1966-1972 (Box 1336, Folder 37)
- Bob Dole, 1996 (Box 1336, Folder 38)
- Joseph Egan, 1983 (Box 1336, Folder 39)
- East Asia, 2001 (Box 1336, Folder 40-43)
- East Asia, 2001 (Box 1337, Folder 1-3)
- Environment, 1985 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 4)
- Erie, 1985 (Box 1337, Folder 5)
- Family, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 6)
- Sally Field and Diane Keaton at cancer hearing, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 7)
- S. David Fineman, 1995 (Box 1337, Folder 8)
- Mike Fisher, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 9)
- Fishing, 1988 (Box 1337, Folder 10)
- Gerald Ford, undated (Box 1337, Folder 11)
- Friends of Cancer Research, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 12)
- Muammar Gaddafi, undated (Box 1337, Folder 13)
- Rudy Giuliani, 1994-1995 (Box 1337, Folder 14)
- Global Dialogue on the New World Order, 1991 (Box 1337, Folder 15)
- Whoopi Goldberg, 1994 (Box 1337, Folder 16)
- Al Gore, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 17)
- Karoly Grosz, 1989 (Box 1337, Folder 18)
- Group photos, 1983-1997 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 19)
- Hawaii, 2001 (Box 1337, Folder 20)
- Healthcare, 1991 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 21)
- Hearings, 1995 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 22)
- John Heinz, undated (Box 1337, Folder 23)
- Elsie Hillman and Ronald Reagan, 1980 (Box 1337, Folder 24)
- Bob Hope, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 25)
- Saddam Hussein, 1990 (Box 1337, Folder 26)
- Individual photos, 1986 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 27)
- Infrastructure, undated (Box 1337, Folder 28)
- International Educator's Conference, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 29)
- Julius Irving, Strom Thurmond, 1983 (Box 1337, Folder 30)
- Jobs and industry, 1983-1996 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 31)
- Michael Jordan, 1987 (Box 1337, Folder 32)
- Judges, 1990 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 33)
- Kiev, 1999 (Box 1337, Folder 34)
- Local trips, 1998 (Box 1337, Folder 35)
- Frederica Massiah-Jackson, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 36)
- Middle East, 1982-2003 (Box 1337, Folder 37)
- Middle East, 1989 (Box 1337, Folder 38)
- Mobile Breast Care Center, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 39)
- Lazar Mojsov, 1988 (Box 1337, Folder 40)
- Hosni Mubarak, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 41)
- Tim Murphy, undated (Box 1337, Folder 42)
- National Association of Lettercarriers, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 43)
- National Rifle Association, 2004 (Box 1337, Folder 44)
- Naval base, 1990 (Box 1337, Folder 45)
- Richard Nixon, 1994 (Box 1337, Folder 46)
- Herbert Olivieri, 1967 (Box 1337, Folder 47)
- Panama, 1990 (Box 1337, Folder 48)
- Passport photos, undated (Box 1337, Folder 49)
- Pennsylvania Building and Construction Trades Council, undated (Box 1337, Folder 50)
- Philadelphia Major League Baseball All-Star Game, 1996 (Box 1337, Folder 51)
- Philadelphia: Past, Present and Future, 1982 (Box 1337, Folder 52)
- Philadelphia race for charity, 1999 (Box 1337, Folder 53)
- Pittsburgh, 1991 (Box 1337, Folder 54)
- Portraits, 1988 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 55)
- PPG visit, 2000s (Box 1337, Folder 56)
- Prairiesta, 1991 (Box 1337, Folder 57)
- Presidential campaign, 1995 (Box 1337, Folder 58)
- Press conferences, 1986-1995 and undated (Box 1337, Folder 59)
- Press stills, undated (Box 1337, Folder 60)
- Ronald Reagan, 1980s (Box 1337, Folder 61)
- Ronald Reagan and Dick Thornburgh, 1984 (Box 1337, Folder 62)
- Red Zone Robotics, undated (Box 1337, Folder 63)
- Republican National Convention, 1996 (Box 1337, Folder 64)
- Republican State Committee of Pennsylvania, 1991 (Box 1337, Folder 65)
- Tom Ridge, undated (Box 1337, Folder 66)
- Rochester Institute of Technology Board of Trustees meeting, 1997 (Box 1337, Folder 67)
- Charles Rosenberry, undated (Box 1337, Folder 68)
- Karen Royden, 1995 (Box 1337, Folder 69)
- Rick Santorum, undated (Box 1338, Folder 1)
- Senate Intelligence Committee hearing, 1996 (Box 1338, Folder 2)
- South America, 1989 (Box 1338, Folder 3)
- South Korea, 2001 (Box 1338, Folder 4-5)
- Staff, undated (Box 1338, Folder 6)
- Steamtown, 1990 (Box 1338, Folder 7)
- Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation, 1997 (Box 1338, Folder 8)
- Taiwan, 2001 (Box 1338, Folder 9)
- Dick Thornburgh, undated (Box 1338, Folder 10)
- Strom Thurmond, 1997 (Box 1338, Folder 11)
- Town halls, 1984-1985 (Box 1338, Folder 12)
- Kathleen Turner, undated (Box 1338, Folder 13)
- United Research Laboratories visit, 2004 (Box 1338, Folder 14)
- US Army European operations, 1982 (Box 1338, Folder 15)
- USS Dwight D. Eisenhower, undated (Box 1338, Folder 16)
- Valley Forge Military Academy, 1982 (Box 1338, Folder 17)
- Veterans, 1991 and undated (Box 1338, Folder 18)
- Veterans Affairs Committee, 1994 (Box 1338, Folder 19)
- Reggie Walton, 1989 (Box 1338, Folder 20)
- Watchdog of the Treasury, 1990 (Box 1338, Folder 21)
- Widerner University, 1990 (Box 1338, Folder 22)